Miller, Howard F.; Papers apap088
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Howard F. Miller Papers
1939-1983
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Miller, Howard F.
apap088
8.4 cubic ft.
Miller was an expert on institutional budgetary finance. He served on the faculty of the Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University (1947-1969), as deputy director of the New York State Division of the Budget (1971-1978), and director of the budget, (1978-1980).
Biographical History
Dr. Howard F. "Red" Miller was born on August 18, 1920 in Buffalo, NY. He graduated Syracuse University in 1942 with a bachelor's degree in Political Science and Journalism where he was a member of the Phi Gamma Delta fraternity.
At the start of World War II, he entered the United States Army as a private. During the course of the war, he rose to the rank of 1st Lieutenant in the Army Corps of Engineers. He served in the United States and the European theater of operations. He was wounded in action and awarded the Purple Heart and Bronze Star for bravery.
After being honorably discharged from the Army in 1945 he attended Harvard University, earning a master's degree in Public Administration in 1947 and a doctorate in Government in 1955. From 1947 to 1969 he was on the faculty of the Maxwell School of Public Affairs at Syracuse University. From 1948 to 1955 he served as the administrative assistant to the Dean of the Maxwell Graduate School. In the summer of 1952 he worked as a research consultant to the Department of the Army in preparation for an Army Comptroller program at Syracuse University.
In 1956 Syracuse University granted Miller teaching leave to serve as an administrative deputy to the New York State (NYS) Division of the Budget. He held that position until 1959 when he became a consultant to the NYS Department of Audit and Control to coordinate and write the Annual Report of the State Comptroller. From 1962 to 1965 he acted as the fiscal advisor to the Minority Leader of the NYS Assembly, Representative Anthony Travia. Miller became secretary of the Assembly Ways and Means Committee in 1965 and served as such till 1968. In this capacity he participated in the NYS Constitutional Convention of 1967.
From 1968 through June of 1981 Miller served in various appointed NYS government posts; executive director of the NYS Social Development Planning Commission, 1968 to 1971, deputy director of the NYS Division of the Budget, 1971 to 1977, and director of the NYS Division of the Budget in 1978, a position directly appointed by Governor Hugh L. Carey. In 1971, continuing into 1972, he took leave from the Division of the Budget to serve as executive director of the Scott Commission, created to study government operations in New York City.
For his government service, Syracuse University presented Miller with the George Arents Award for excellence in government in 1973. He was further honored in 1982, receiving the Nelson A. Rockefeller Award for distinguished public service.
Miller resigned from public service for health reasons in June 1981. He lived in Delmar, NY until his death on February 17, 1999. He was survived by his wife Peg and two sons.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the personal papers of Dr. Howard F. Miller spanning the years 1939-1983. It consists of correspondence, teaching material, legislative reports, legislative hearings, position papers, daily journals, news clippings and press releases. The papers chiefly relate to his service on the faculty of the Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University, 1947-1969, his time as a New York State public servant for the Division of the Budget, 1956-1981, and his service on the New York State Constitutional Convention of 1967.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Series 1: Teaching and Scholarship, 1939-1964, undated
Series 2: New York State Constitutional Convention, 1966-1968, 1973, 1977, undated
Series 3: Public Service, 1941-1983, undated
Acquisition Information
Dr. Howard Miller gave a third (Series 2) of the items in this manuscript group directly to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in 1982. Syracuse University transferred the remaining items (Series 1 and 3) to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, in 2006. Syracuse University received those papers directly from Miller in 1968.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Public Servants; Political Science; Politics and Politicians; College teaching -- New York (State); Budget -- New York (State); Fiscal policy -- New York (State); New York (State) -- Politics and government.; Albany (N.Y.); Syracuse (N.Y.); Miller, Howard, 1920-1999.; Travia, Anthony J.; Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs.; Syracuse University.; New York (State). Division of the Budget.; New York (State). Legislature.; New York (State). Constitutional Convention (1967); New York (State). Division of the Budget -- Appropriations and expenditures.; United States. Army.
- Teaching and Scholarship, 1939-1964; 1; 1.75 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains papers pertaining to Dr. Miller's days as both a student and a professor at Harvard University and the Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs. Important papers include lecture notes, unpublished political science papers from significant scholars, teaching materials, copies of exams, case studies, syllabi, and reprints of published articles used for research. Courses which he taught include Public Administration, Public Budgeting, Federal Budgeting, Administrative and Fiscal Budget, Fiscal Policy, and Army Comptrollership School classes. Many documents contained in "undated" folders refer to material that was not authored by Dr. Miller, but presumably used for instruction in his courses. Some folders contain case studies that may have been used in course instruction. Not all dates are inclusive. Series 1 ends in Box 2 with Folder 23.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Political Science Papers, 1.1 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 1)
    - For Future Madisons by Paul H. Appleby, Undated
    - Federal Administrative Regions by James W Fesler, Undated
    - Philosophy, Science and Art of Public Administration by Charles A. Beard, 1939
    - Does Bureaucracy Menace America by Jonathan Daniels, 1944
    - Riot of the Unemployed at Trenton, NJ 1935 by Chester I. Barnard, 1945; Undated
  - Political Science Papers, 1.2 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 2)
    - Tax Policies for Prosperity by Beardsley Ruml, 1946
    - Civilian Control of a Department of National Defense by Paul H. Appleby, 1946
    - Political Science Back Home by John M. Gaus, 1950
    - Ethical Standards in Government by US Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, 1951
  - Federal Budget - Secondary Sources, 1947-1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 3-5)
  - Teaching Materials - Published Articles Reprints, 1947; 1950; 1954; 1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 6)
  - Public Administration - Course Material, Secondary Sources, 1947-1963 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 7-8)
  - Public Budgeting, Public Administration, Other Course Materials, 1948; 1950-1956; 1958-1962; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 9-12)
  - Public Budgeting Course Materials, 1950-1955; 1959-1963; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 13)
  - Federal Budget - Course Materials, 1950; 1953; 1954; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 14)
  - Fiscal Policy, 1950; 1954; 1958; 1960; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 15)
  - Public Budgeting - Course Materials, 1950; 1958-1959; 1964 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 16)
  - Administrative and Fiscal Budget, 1950; 1960; 1963; 1964 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 17)
  - Public Administration - Course Material, Correspondence, Secondary Sources, 1951; 1954-1956; 1958-1961; 1964 Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 18)
  - Political Science - Class Notes, Paper Excerpts, Case Studies, 1952; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 19)
  - Public Budgeting - Course Materials, 1952-1964; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 20)
  - "The Army Budget Process" - Paper by Miller for the Army Comptrollership School, Other Materials, 1952; 1954; 1959 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 21)
  - Army Comptrollership School Budgeting Course - Class Materials, 1953; Undated (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 22)
  - Political Science Papers - Course Materials, 1963 (Box 1 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 23)
  - Performance Budgeting - Course Materials, 1954; 1958; 1960-1963 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 1-2)
  - Political Science Papers, 1.19 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 3)
    - Financial Problems of a Larger State by Robert S. Herman, 1954
    - Work Status Reporting in the Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation Service by Jerome A. Miles, 1962
    - Yardstick for Performance by John H. Dwyer, 1962
  - Teaching Materials - Published Article Reprints, 1955 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 4-5)
  - Political Science - Course Materials, 1956; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 6)
  - Public Administration - Course Material, 1957; 1959-1960; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 7-8)
  - Inter-university Case Program: Correspondence with Deans Regarding Case Studies, 1959-1961 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 9)
  - Army Comptrollership School Performance Budgeting - Course Materials, 1959-1962; 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 10-11)
  - Correspondence Relating to the Maxwell School, 1960-1964 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 12)
  - Teaching Materials - Lecture Notes, 1960; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 13)
  - Case Studies on Mental Health, License Plates, Financial Management, 1960; 1961; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 14)
  - Secondary Source Material, 1961; 1962; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 15)
  - Teaching Materials - Exams & Syllabi, 1962; 1964; Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 16)
  - Albany Graduate Program Institutional Budgeting, 1962; 1964 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 17)
  - Student Papers, 1.31 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 18)
    - The Ethical Problem of an Elected Political Executive by Stephen K. Bailey
    - Public Administration by Dwight Waldo, 1963
    - The Budget Bureau Gives Advice; Glamour Girl vs Plain Janes
  - A Manual for Budgeting Techniques for Local Governments, 1963 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 19)
  - Teaching Materials - Published Article Reprints, Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 20)
  - Teaching Materials - Published Article Reprints, Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 21)
  - Political Science Papers, undated; 1.35 (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 22)
    - A Factual Summary of State Administrative Reorganization by William H. Edwards
    - Behavior Studies for Labor Peace by Russell Porter
    - A Scale to Measure Effectiveness of Police Functioning by Spencer D. Parratt
    - The Need for Career Administrators by W.W. Stockberger
    - The Profession of the Public Service by W.E. Mosher
    - The Place of Administration in Government by Charles A. Beard
    - Administration as a Profession by Leonard D. White
    - Avenues of Advance in Public Administration by Herbert Etterich
  - Article on Performance Budgeting, Author: possibly Burkhead, Undated (Box 2 (1-Teaching and Scholarship), Folder 23)
- New York State Constitutional Convention, 1966-1968; 1973; 1977; Undated; 2; approximately .75 cubic ft.
  This series contains Dr. Miller's personal papers in regards to the Constitutional Convention of 1967. Important papers included are summaries of legislations, legislative reports, newspaper clippings, correspondence and reports relating to finance for the New York State Constitutional Convention.
  The Constitutional Convention of 1967 was the ninth such convention in New York State history. The purpose of the Convention was to eliminate obsolete and confusing provisions and remove unnecessary detail from the extremely lengthy document. New Yorkers ultimately rejected the proposed changes to the Constitution in the 1967 election.
  Series 2 begins with Folder 24 in Box 2. There are two bound volumes that are housed within Special Collections, but outside of this collection, pertaining to the New York State Constitutional Convention. See also Summary of Legislation 1966 Packet 1 in Series 3 for related Constitutional Convention information.
  - Background to the 1967 Constitutional Convention, 1966 (Box 2 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 24)
  - "Towards an Effective Constitutional Convention: Recommendations for Legislation", 1966 (Box 2 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 25)
  - Index to Committees & Meetings, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 2 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 26)
  - Committee on State Finance, General Convention & Confidential Materials, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 2 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 27)
  - State of New York Temporary State Commission on the Constitutional Convention Reports, Volumes 1-8, 1966-1967
    SPE KFN 5680 1967 A15.
  - State of New York Temporary State Commission on the Constitutional Convention Reports, Volumes 9-16, 1967
  - Proposed New Constitution - Text, Abstract and Highlights, 1967 (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 1)
  - Working Drafts & Position Papers - Taxes, State Debt & Budgeting, 1967; Undated (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 2-3)
  - Committee on State Finance - Correspondence & Related Material, gift & loans provision, 1967 (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 4)
  - Committee on State Finance - Final Reports & Related Materials, 1967; Undated (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 5-9)
  - Committee on State Finance - Working Drafts & Research Materials, 1967; Undated (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 11)
  - Highlights of the Proposed Constitution, 1967 (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1967; 1968 (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 13)
  - League of Women Voters Materials, 1973; 1977; Undated (Box 3 (2-New York State Constitutional Convention), Folder 14)
- Public Service, 1941-1983, undated; 3; approximately 5.9 cubic ft.
  This series contains reports, correspondence and news releases related to Dr. Miller's time served in the New York State (NYS) Government with the bulk of materials dating from 1955-1967 and the early 1980s. The most prominent position he held was that of director of the NYS Division of the Budget. Important papers include NYS budget reference material, reports, and correspondence, a series of articles he wrote for the Albany Times Union, papers from when he was a consultant to the NYS Department of Audit and Control and a fiscal advisor to the Minority Leader of the NYS Assembly, correspondence, position papers and voting documents of the NYS Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education, and budget recommendations relating to public schools. Not all dates are inclusive.
  It should be noted that this series does not end when he retires in 1981; he continued to stay in contact with members of the government who took his place.
  - Budget Divisions in different states, correspondence, notes, 1941; 1946; 1951; 1953-1957; 1961; 1962; Undated (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 15-16)
  - Training and Experience, 1943; Undated (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1945-1963 (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 18)
  - Capital Construction Secondary Sources and Research Materials, 1947-1962 (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 19)
  - Budget Execution Conference Material, 1949; 1952; 1959 (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 20-21)
  - Army Budgeting - Secondary sources, Personal Notes, Minutes, 1953-1954; Undated (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 22)
  - Capital Construction - funding information, maps, etc, 1954-1956; Undated (Box 3 (3-Public Service), Folder 23)
  - New York State Division of Budget Administrative Deputy - Correspondence and Reference Material, 1955; 1956; 1958; 1960; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 1)
  - Bureau of the Budget - Internal Documents, 1955-1958 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 2)
  - New York State Legislative reports, Correspondence, Summaries Regarding Budget, 1955; 1960; 1965-1968 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 3)
  - State debt - Outgo documents, 1955; 1963; 1964; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 4)
  - Personal Correspondence - Regarding New York State Highway Funding, Ethics, Whiteface Mountain, etc, 1956; 1957 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 5)
  - New York State Budget Material, Questions, Correspondence, 1956; 1958; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 6)
  - New York State Budget - Incentives, Hiring, Promotion, 1957; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 7)
  - Examiner's Summary of Budget Requests and Budget Recommendations, 1957 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 8)
  - New York State Budget Dept. Correspondence, 1957; 1959 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Regarding Capital Construction, 1958 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 10)
  - Basic Data Book - New York State Budget, 1958; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 11)
  - New York State Budget Training Material, 1958; 1959; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 12)
  - Behind the State Budget articles written for the Albany Times Union, 1961 February (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 13)
  - Consultant to the New York State Department of Audit & Control, 1961; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 14)
  - Reference Material for Multiregional Conferences on Budget & Fiscal Subjects, 1961 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 15)
  - Social Development Planning committee Correspondence, 1961; 1969; 1971 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 16)
  - Minutes of Senate Finance Committee Budget Request, Department of Social Welfare, 1963 February 23 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 17)
  - Miller's letters requesting bond information on behalf of Minority Leader Travia, 1964 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 18)
  - Fiscal Advisor, 1964; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 19)
  - New York State Department of Health: Tuberculosis, Mental Hygiene reports, 1964; Undated (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 20)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate Comparison of State Paid or Estimated to be Paid to School Districts by School Year, 1965 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 21)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate - State Expenditures for Local Assistance State Operations and Capital Construction by Function and Organization 1965-1966 Compared with Prior Years (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 22)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate Total State Aid by Function and by Category: Comparative Analysis State Fiscal Year 1965-1966 Compared with Prior Years (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 23)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate - Summary of Legislation - 1965 Session - Packet 1-3 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 24)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate - Summary of Legislation - 1965 Session - Packet 4-6 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 25)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate - Summary of Legislation - 1965 Session - Packet 7 (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 26)
  - New York State Assembly Analysis of 1965-1966 and 1966-1967 School Aid Increases and Tax Equivalents by School Districts and School Year (Box 4 (3-Public Service), Folder 27)
  - Summary of Legislation News From Speaker Travia, 1965-1966; Undated (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 1)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate - Summary of Legislation - Position Papers, 1965-1966; Undated (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 2)
  - Secretary of the Assembly Ways & Means Committee, 1965; 1967; Undated (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 3)
  - Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee Minutes - Budget Requests of Department of Education, Albany, 1966 February 23 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 4)
  - Department of Health - Minutes of the Proceedings of a Public Hearing of the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee with Reference to Budget, 1966 February 24 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 5)
  - Department of Labor - Minutes of the Proceedings of a Public Hearing of the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee with Reference to Budget, 1966 February 24 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 6)
  - Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee Meeting Minutes - Budget Requests of the Human Rights Commission, 1966 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 7)
  - Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee Meeting Minutes - Budget Requests of the Division for Youth, 1966 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 8)
  - Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee Meeting Minutes - Budget Requests of the Department of Mental Hygiene, 1966 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 9)
  - Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee Meeting Minutes - Budget Requests of the Civil Defense Commission, 1966 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 10)
  - Appointment as Delegate to Conference of the National Tax Association, 1966 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 11)
  - New York State Assembly - Correspondence, Vote Sheets and Position Papers, 1966 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 12)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Correction, 1967 February 20 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 13)
  - Minutes of Legislative Budget Hearings - New York State Identification and Intelligence System, 1967 February 20 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 14)
  - Legislative Budget Hearings - Division of Parole, 1967 February 20 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 15)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Mental Hygiene, 1967 February 21 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 16)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Division of Housing and Community renewal, 1967 February 22 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 17)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Public Works, 1967 February 22 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 18)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Assembly Parlor, The Capitol, Conservation Department, 1967 February 22 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 19)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Metropolitan commuter Transportation Authority, 1967 February 22 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 20)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Health, 1967 February 23 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 21)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Social Welfare, 1967 February 23 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 22)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Department of Education, 1967 February 24 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 23)
  - Legislative Budget Hearing - Held in Assembly Parlor, 1967 February 24 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 24)
  - Legislative Budget Hearings - Council on the Arts, 1967 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 25)
  - Minutes of Legislative Budget Hearing on Department of Commerce, Job Development Authority, 1967 February 25 (Box 5 (3-Public Service), Folder 26)